<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Words on I like to explain things </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/words/index.xml/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 11:05:52 EST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>memory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 11:05:52 EST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/memory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I took a course from coursera on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/learning&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;learning how to learn&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.
I was planning on writing about it since it&amp;rsquo;s universally applicable to all
who wish to learn about how the brain works. Turns out it fit the criteria for
the final assignment, so double win. Since I took notes as I went through the
course, the text is more like summarized notes. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Thinking modes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two different types of brain processing that occur almost mutually
exclusively. The first is called &amp;ldquo;focused&amp;rdquo; and occurs when one is processing
concrete thoughts; it&amp;rsquo;s also closely associated with intense concentration.
The other is called &amp;ldquo;diffused&amp;rdquo; and occurs when new problems are encountered or
abstract ideas are involved. The diffused mode occurs when thoughts are free
to wonder, such as while taking a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easier to create and be creative in diffused mode. One way to make sure
you&amp;rsquo;re in diffused mode is to make sure to NOT follow an outline. A mind map
can be a good alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Storage modes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working memory can only store about four things (which is smaller than I had
last been told). Long term memory is like a warehouse and sometimes can
require time to &amp;ldquo;look things up&amp;rdquo;. This is why sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll remember things
much later than when you were trying to recall them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both modes are strengthened by practice and repetition, called spaced
repetition. The passage of time and repeated learning allows time for the new
neural structures to form, which allows a memory to persist. Persistence is
also improved by a good night&amp;rsquo;s sleep as that is the time the brain uses to
rid itself of toxins and restructure memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Executing learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the brain uses two different memory modes, going back and forth
between words and images is one method of activating both areas of the brain.
Another similar concept is known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0fKBhvDjuy0&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;powers of ten&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which involves changing the perspective by zooming in and out by powers of
ten. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s the perspective change that&amp;rsquo;s important rather than the
magnitude of difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A practical example of chaging perspective is a painter putting a dot of paint
on a canvas and then taking a few steps back to see how it looks a little
farther away. Another example is simply shifting from writing sitting down to
standing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastination can hinder learning, but it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that the
pain associated with starting an unpleasant activitity will go away shortly
after beginning. The pomodoro technique was created to help combat putting
things off by providing a burst of productivity while also giving a reward for
completion at the end. (I can&amp;rsquo;t help but think of the phrase &amp;ldquo;just do it&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;How memories are formed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chunk is a piece of information bound together in the brain. Chunks are
built by focused attention, understanding, and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottom up learning as well as gaining a high level overview is best for
complete subject mastery. Applying these two concepts together is what forms
the context to put all the individual chunks together, sort of like putting
together a puzzle. Understanding is like superglue that helps hold the
underlying memory traces together. Simply trying to help recall what you have
learned also helps understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Determining subject mastery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing and recall are the best methods of determining level of competence.
Both methods should be done in different settings to ensure the learned
material is not dependent on subconscience traits of a given place. Testing
oneself and practicing the hard problems are a great way to ensure you don&amp;rsquo;t
prematurely believe that you have mastered the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A benefit of subject mastery is that the chunks all become weaved together
such that they only take one position in working memory. The information
becomes compressed together such that more information is available for recall
with mastered content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some general notes about mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One should not be discouraged if something doesn&amp;rsquo;t come easily. Persistence
is more important than being intelligent!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diving into something completely randomly isn&amp;rsquo;t the most effective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overlearning is effective if spaced out, but don&amp;rsquo;t trick yourself into doing
so with the easiest material and think it means full mastery has occurred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first principle is that you must not fool yourself - and you are the
easiest person to fool. - Richard Feynman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interweaving between concepts, ideas, and disciplines allows creativity and
flexbility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Defeating procrastination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to achieve tackling procrastination is to focus on the process rather
than the product. Forming good habits surrounding your learning is key, which
are made up of several parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cue - a stimulus that may cause your attention to divert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The routine - how you feel and react while learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reward - the emotional payoff for completing an amount of work (Also,
the better you get at something, the more you will enjoy it.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The belief - basically, believing success is possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Good habits to utilize&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a planner journal, both for weekly and daily tasks. Doing so will free
brain power to work on actual tasks rather than the task list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plan your quitting time, it&amp;rsquo;s as important as planning your start time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the hardest things in the day first, also described as eating your frogs
first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delay rewards until you finish a given task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop trying to be impressive, just strive for clarity. Ironically, when
focusing on just being clear, the work ends up being impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while, do something different such as a walk around the block.
Especially when you get stuck on something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;Memory techniques (more executing learning)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handwriting can be a good technique to utilize as the hand motions involved
assist with recall. Also, associating concepts with images can help as well.
Sometimes the best images to assist with memorization are the more strange
ones. A &amp;ldquo;memory palace&amp;rdquo; is a specific mental model of placing images in a
place, such as your house to help group things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach for creating meaning groups of things is to use a nmeumonic,
such as the first letter of each word to make a silly sentence. Metaphors or
analogies work well too. Sometimes it can be helpful to pretend you are the
concept you are trying to understand, for example an atom of copper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above practices combat Einstellung - being blocked by thinking
about a problem in the wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody is actually good at multitasking. If you think you are, you&amp;rsquo;re worse at
it then you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_8&#34;&gt;Problem solving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at a problem is in parts by breaking it down. Think about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are you trying to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you want to achieve?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What information do you have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A given problem does not have to be done quickly. Lastly, it&amp;rsquo;s important to
know there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know that solving the problem is not the hard part, it&amp;rsquo;s getting your mind
familiar enough with the problem to get ready to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_9&#34;&gt;Differences between people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier it was said that people have around four &amp;ldquo;slots&amp;rdquo; in working memory.
However, not everybody is the same and some may have less than others. But the
less areas of working memory that one has, the easier is to move into diffused
mode and be more creative. The same trade off is true for those who have can
hold more in their working memory. These people are able to focus on more
concepts at a time, but aren&amp;rsquo;t able to as easily enter into diffused mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody&amp;rsquo;s natural learning ability is different, but changing the way you
think can allow you to achieve that which even natural born geniouses don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also grow at different rates. The myelin sheath is a fatty insulation
on the neuron that helps signal mood more quickly. In some people it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
fully develop until they reach their 20s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_10&#34;&gt;Ensuring sufficient preparation for a test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many others were included in the course, but I thought these were the most
important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you make a serious effort to understand the text?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you work on the problems individually?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you work with classmates on homework problems and contribute actively
to the discusion?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you consult with the instructor when you were having trouble?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you understand ALL of the homework problems?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you get a reasonable amount of sleep?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like common sense, but I wish somebody had told me these things while I was
still in school!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_11&#34;&gt;During the exam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revisiting your work and not powering through is a way of allowing your entire
brain to work, giving the right hemisphere a chance to work. The left
hemisphere can quite often be overly confident and provides the analytical way
of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start on a hard problem, but then abort it so you can let the diffused mode
work on it some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a contigency plan for the worst case scenario. This allows your mind to
enter without worry knowing failure isn&amp;rsquo;t the end of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_12&#34;&gt;Final advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study the great people of your field or whatever you&amp;rsquo;re trying to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A book that may be worth reading:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Fluent-Months-Anyone-Language-Anywhere/dp/0062282697&#34;&gt;Fluent in 3 MONTHS&lt;/a&gt;
- describes how to learn a new language faster than what most believe is
required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_13&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew! That turned out to be way longer than I thought. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a good
summary of the course though and hopefully is a good reference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>